Hi, I'm Sandra, from HEARa.
Welcome to Day 3 of our 10
day Lipreading Challenge.
designed to help you develop and
practice your lip reading skills!
Hearing loss can have a
profound impact on your life.
It touches every interaction.
It can affect your career,
your relationships,
and your happiness.
Join me to explore tips and
tricks on this YouTube channel
to bring confidence and clarity to relationships
in all areas of your life.
Today we're moving on to
a new group of homophenes.
YES!!
But before we do that, what's a homophene again?
Homophenes are groups of sounds
that look alike on the lips.
If you haven't already watched the
first two days of the challenge,
I recommend starting there.
The F and V sounds are homophenes.
To make these sounds, your upper
teeth come to your lower lip.
Watch:
belief
believe
These two words look exactly the same,
even though they don't sound the same at all.
It is possible to confuse these two words,
because the only difference between them is just a fraction of a second
of vibration of your vocal cords.
If your attention is elsewhere for that fraction of a second,
or if there's some background noise covering up a word or two,
you could confuse these two words.
That's why substitution practice is important.
We do this so that we can quickly switch gears
when the first thing we see
or hear does not make sense.
Substitution practice is a good exercise
because it gets your mind in that switching mode
where you're substituting one sound for another.
That helps us to stay flexible.
In our substitution practice today,
I'm going to say a sentence with an F or V error
and I want you to make the substitution:
an F for V, or vice versa.
As usual the answers are written in
the section below the video frame.
Are you ready?
Number 1: Sugar is the new vat.
Number 2: It's hot in here, turn on the van.
Number 3: That grape fine is
taking over the backyard.
Number 4: There are many vicious in the sea.
Are you finding it way easier when there's
only two sounds in the homophene group?
Versus three in day 1.
Let's amp up the difficulty a little bit.
Number 5: He apologized to no a fail.
Number 6: I am alone in pie believe.
Number 7: We will have to hire
a van to poof the furniture.
Number 8: The tennis player won his surf.
Number 9: I went skiing in fail this year.
Number 10: I don't like the
saying, Appy wife, appy live.
H is invisible, remember?
That's it for our substitution practice today,
but I wanted to talk a little bit
about flexibility before you go.
Someone once said about lip reading:
I'm stubborn.
If I think I've seen a word, I
hang on to it like a terrier.
Sometimes we have to let go of the
first thought that comes to mind
to find a better word or phrase
with a similar lip shape.
This is one of the hallmarks of a good lip reader,
this ability to let go.
When we get really good at this,
we can do it in real time
to make that quick substitution
and find something else that makes sense.
Yesterday, in day 2 I said about context:
when you know what the context is,
you can anticipate what follows.
Except when you're wrong
about what the context is!
So for example,
you see and hear the word flower,
but if what follows is about
wheat free and chickpea flour,
then you're going to have
to drop your anticipation
of wildflowers and flowery meadows
and start to tune in to the concept of baking.
I'd like to show you how this could
make the conversation go sideways.
Let's say I said the word vlog.
There was some background noise,
so you didn't hear it, but you did see it.
A vlog is a blog in the medium of video.
A word that looks similar to vlog is flaw,
because the G is invisible.
Watch:
vlog
flaw.
I'm going to work on my vlog.
You only have one flaw?
Are you asking me or telling me?
What??
Remember to pay attention to any mismatch
between what you thought
you saw
and facial expression and body language.
If the other person is
frowning or looking confused,
then you may have misunderstood.
Stay flexible and clarify what you thought you saw.
That's all for today.
Thank you for joining me.
I hope you found this helpful.
Tomorrow, we'll get some practice
lip reading F and V sounds in sentences.
In the meantime, please like my video,
subscribe to my channel,
and share this with others.
I'd really appreciate it.
Pie!
I mean, Bye!